[Music]
one of the most annoying sayings I hear
in the magic the Gathering communities
is reading the card explains the card
and while yes that does hold true more
often than not let's have a look at this
card here progenitus a 10 Mana 1010 with
protection from everything whoa
protection from everything that sounds
pretty impressive and as every snooty
magic player has told us reading the
card explains the card so this is pretty
self-explanatory right this creature has
literal protection from everything right
hold on a second
what is that is that an asterisk okay so
what does protection from everything
really mean as always let's start at the
source of Truth the comprehensive rules
rules
702.16 J tells us everything we need to
know about protection from everything to
summarize protection from everything
means that a player or permanent with
that ability can't be the target of
spells or abilities of any kind they
can't be enchanted by auras and
permanence can't be equipped by
equipment fortified by fortifications or
blocked by creatures and all damage that
would be dealt to them is prevented so
that lists out a lot of things but
that's certainly not everything that
cards in Magic the Gathering can dish
out let's cover the things that
protection from everything doesn't
protect you or your permanence from to
start non-targeted destruction or Exile
effects can get around protection from
everything cards like wrath of God or
farewell are perfect exam samples even
black Sun Zenith or toxic Deluge can
kill a creature with protection from
everything if you have enough Mana or
life don't forget about edict effects
too cards like diabolict edict
shieldridge edict and soul shatter can
force an opponent to sacrifice their
creature with protection from everything
if it's their only creature on the
battlefield or in the case of Soul
shatter-like effects if it has the
highest Mana value it's important to
note though that this non-targeted
exception doesn't apply to everything
Blasphemous act for example will not
destroy progenitus this is because
Blasphemous act specifically deals
damage to the creature and protection
from everything prevents all damage that
would be dealt to it now that's
something to keep in mind for players
too if a player has protection from
everything damage dealt to them will
certainly be prevented but protection
from everything says nothing about
losing life so cards like Bond of Agony
and exam grenade can still get around
protection from everything it's
non-targeting and it's not dealing
damage remember damage causes loss of
light but life loss is not damage
another non-targeting ability that
people often forget about is proliferate
proliferate lets you choose any number
of permanents or players that have
counters on them and they get an
additional counter of each type they
already have and as per the rules this
ability doesn't Target so if you have an
opponent who is on nine poison counters
and they have just played the one ring
to give themselves protection from
everything you can still take them out
of the game simply by proliferating and
giving them that final poison counter
one final way to get around protection
from everything is almost exclusively
reserved for those playing red now there
are two green cards that do the special
thing we want but one of them is Whipple
will and its ability targets so it
doesn't help out here the other one has
an ability list so long nobody actually
remembers what it does so we'll go over
that shortly what we're looking for is
cards that say damage can't be prevented
an important rule to know about is Rule
101.2 when a rule or effect allows or
directs something to happen and another
rule states that it can't happen that
can't affect takes precedence so while
protection from everything says all
damage that would be dealt to a
permanent or player is prevented flaring
pain would allow cards like Blasphemous
act to deal damage to creatures or allow
you to deal damage to a player speaking
of one of questing Beats many lines of
text says combat damage that would be
dealt by creatures you control can't be
prevented so if you attack a player who
has protection from everything questing
beasts will allow all of that damage to
go through it's worth noting that some
of these damage prevention effects do
require a Target in order for them to
resolve a classic example that you might
see in today's meta is players casting
The Stomp path of Bone Crusher Giant on
themselves or one of their creatures
purely to bypass a creatureless player
who has just cast the one ring so now
you know how to get around protection
from everything but did you know with
just two cards you can permanently steal
creatures from players while playing in
red and white want to learn more well
check out this video here
thank you so much for watching and I'll
see you in the next one